Contact

shawhintalebi@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/shawhintalebi (LinkedIn) youtube.com/c/ShawhinTalebi

(Blog) shawhin.medium.com/ (Blog)

www.shawhintalebi.com/ (Company)

Top Skills

Public Speaking
Product Development
Product Management

Honors-Awards

Student Leader of the Year - Nominee

Outstanding Undergraduate Student - Nominee

2019 Weeks of Welcome (WoW) Poster Competition - 3rd Place

2021 Friends of BrainHealth Visionary New Scientist - Finalist

Publications

Using Machine Learning for the Calibration of Airborne Particulate Sensors

Machine Learning for Light Sensor Calibration

Data-Driven EEG Band Discovery with Decision Trees

Decoding Physical and Cognitive Impacts of Particulate Matter Concentrations at Ultra-Fine Scales

Modeling Autonomic Pupillary Responses from External Stimuli Using Machine Learning

Shaw Talebi

Al Educator | PhD, Physics

Plano, Texas, United States

Summary

Meet Shaw, a data scientist, entrepreneur, researcher, content creator, drummer, and bread enthusiast driven by an insatiable curiosity to understand the world and create better systems.

With a Ph.D. in Physics from The University of Texas at Dallas, Shaw has over 5 years of experience in data science and project management across diverse fields such as biometric research, credit risk, automotive sales, medicine, human performance, marketing, event planning, and content creation.

As a data scientist, Shaw helps teams solve their problems through data-informed solutions while constantly seeking entrepreneurial opportunities to provide value and tackle challenging problems.

Experience

The Data Entrepreneurs

Founder

January 2023 - Present (1 year 8 months)

Founded a community of 650+ data & AI entrepreneurs. Hosting monthly workshops and discussions.

Shawhin Talebi Ventures LLC

Al Advisor & Educator

December 2020 - Present (3 years 9 months)

Texas. United States

Helping 1-1k person businesses use Al. Custom Al workshops for teams and orgs.

Towards Data Science

Writer

November 2020 - Present (3 years 10 months)

Writing articles on Data Science + Al. 25k Monthly Reads. 9k Followers.

YouTube Content Creator September 2020 - Present (4 years)

Making videos on Data Science + Entrepreneurship. 1M+ Views. 30k+ subs.

Toyota Financial Services Corporation
Data Scientist
June 2022 - July 2023 (1 year 2 months)

Plano, Texas, United States

- Uncovered and corrected issues in production credit risk model that impacted over 70% of accounts and wrote model monitoring scripts to help avoid future failures
- Redeveloped loan originations model for independent dealers, which resulted in a 50% model performance improvement and provided \$2.5 million in realized value to business partner

The University of Texas at Dallas Graduate Research Assistant December 2018 - May 2022 (3 years 6 months) Richardson, TX

- Published open-source methodology to discover optimal EEG bands which led to better characterization of the underlying power spectrum than the more commonly used band boundaries by a factor of 2
- Train over 100 machine learning models which estimated particulate ma]er (PM) concentrations based on a suite of over 300 biometric variables which accurately estimated PM concentrations with high fidelity (r2 = 0.91)
- Led 5 teams focused on deployment of a real-lime Python-based biometrics application, unveiling immediate insights that were previously inaccessible

Palomino Motors
Business & IT Manager
May 2017 - December 2018 (1 year 8 months)
7021 John W Carpenter Fwy

- Analyzed marketing and sales reports to inform inventory acquisition, which resulted in a 50% decrease in average inventory age
- Evaluated costs of lead providers through analysis of lead data and close rates, which led to over \$2500 in monthly savings

The University of Texas at Dallas 1 year 7 months

Executive Chairman - Student Union and Activities Advisory Board May 2016 - May 2017 (1 year 1 month)

Dallas/Fort Worth Area

- Hired, trained, and led team of 8 SUAAB executive council members, that planned and executed 36 events with over 14,000 in total attendance
- Managed and analyzed programming budget of over \$216,000 along with attendance reports to inform future campus events

Music Chairman - Student Union and Activities Advisory Board November 2015 - May 2016 (7 months)

Richardson, TX

- Orchestrated and implemented 2016 Spring Concert with over 1200 students, 45 volunteers, and 6 outside companies and organizations at the TI Plaza, that is now used as a model for all Spring Concerts
- Analyzed aggregate student course schedules to predict optimal event times

Education

The University of Texas at Dallas

Doctor of Philosophy - PhD, Physics · (2020 - 2022)

The University of Texas at Dallas

Master of Science (M.S.), Physics · (2018 - 2019)

The University of Texas at Dallas
Bachelor of Science (B.S.), Physics · (2013 - 2017)